[Music]
Hello I'm Dave Fisher so this is going to
be camp one day one this is the compact
version so I decided to make two
versions of this video one that kind of
like has my family in it which is kind
of like a more camp feel and kind of
like a camp look but there's a little
bit of fluff in those right and so I
thought I'd make another version that's
just me
chugging through the app and admittedly
if you watch this version you might have
to pause at something because the speed
is too fast. The goal is to try
to make it more compact for people that
prefer that style so hopefully you have
your login information you know you went
through you registered for the camp long
ago and you know how to sign in to
tynker right and so I'm going to show
you what it is we're going to make first
so I'm going to start by showing a
finished solution so here's a finished
solution for what we're gonna make today
so we're learning about tynker skills so
tynker is extremely similar to scratch
we're just learning it in tynker where
the monster is following the mouse
different places and we'll learn about
variables right now food is 5 as soon as
he gets it you can see the food went
to four also if you're an astute
observer you'll notice that he's
actually moving a little faster now that
he's got one and so now he's gotten two
so there's only three left and he's
moving even faster if he gets these two
up here now you can see he's kind of bulking it
around the screen one left and then when
he gets it it says you win so that's the
game that we're making together so
what I want you to do is I want you
to log in to tynker I sent you a log
in and hopefully you know how to use
that if you didn't get the one that I
sent you you can still just make your
own account what we're doing here is
free to do we're just creating projects
and doing different things so go ahead
and click on new project make sure you
saw where I clicked there so I clicked on my
projects so the class is like you know up
here in the dashboard and the different
things you can do within projects is
kind of what we're focused on for this
video so I want a new blank project
and what this new blank project is
going to be is it's gonna be called
monster feast sometimes it's
nice to title them right the start that
way you don't forget later and so let's
get more familiar with the tynker
interface so here's the tynker
interface again it's very similar to
scratch in that there's code that you
can use over here that's broken up
into different categories there's the
code for each actor they call actors in
scratch or in tynker instead of sprites
like scratch does this actor right now
has the following code and if I hit play we
can watch what he does and we're going
to understand what this code is so I
want to start that was what I hit this
button set the rotation style to left
and right so he can't like look upwards
on his back he just does left and
right and forever walk at a speed of 10
pixels per every 5 milliseconds five
hundredths of a second and if he's on the
edge you'll notice that he bounces right
getting more familiar with tynker you
can see that in the desktop mode you've
got a stage here and you can make your
stage bigger and smaller with this
handle and you can also click into this
motor here which shows the stage bigger
and then a left panel which I've never
found useful so you can switch
back and forth from the stage in the
code using that button now to be honest
that button is useful for the web but
really that buttons is for iPad users who
can only see one or the other at a time
and so they have to switch back and
forth from code to stage all the time
but we can actually see the stage is
just smaller for a little bit let's go
ahead and see if we can pick some things
up so let's take a look at this code and
let's see if we change some things to change
what happens so if I change his move from 10
to 30 and you can see then he's going to
book it across the stage right so he's
gonna be going really fast if I did
things like taking out this animated
walk I'm gonna put this back so I'm just
going to set it over here then you can
see that he's just kind of like frozen
in that position so we can make changes
to the code we can see how the code
interacts with our actor I'm going to
put this animate walk back in
now it's kind of one of two I'll close up
by the way I was kind of bad there
whenever you're grabbin code in tynker
you can grab that block and all the ones
under it with this left handle or you
can grab just that block with the right
handle so if I wanted to move them all I
would use the left handle if I wanted to
move just that one out I'd use the
right handle and so that's how you move
code is with these handles now people
are in the habit of just grabbing it
from the middle the middle kind of behaves like
the left handle all right
so we're going to fix some things up in
our game the first thing I want to do is
I want the stage to not be wiped so I'm
going to click on the stage its gear
icon when I click on that gear icon I
can see that it's got costumes sounds
and then some advanced things I want a
costume right so I want to look through these
things so I'm gonna click on add background
and the one that I picked was from the
cooking category but for yours feel free
to pick any any backdrop you'd like
right so I'm gonna go with kitchen just
as I think it looks good
once I select it you can see it's
already back there but I do have to
close the style that I opened so now
my little monster is in the kitchen by
the way my little monster here his name
is actor now actor is kind of a terrible
name it's kind of like a human's name
being human right so if you were to name your
baby it's like Oh what am I gonna
make my baby I'm gonna name him human
right I'm gonna call them monster right
and so that's his name you could call
him Bernie or you could call him
whatever you want
right so he is a monster his name is a
appearently monster for me also not a great
name now Monster is gonna go around and
he wants to collect cupcakes so let's go
ahead and make some other cupcakes
cupcakes are called actors sprites in
scratch if you familiar with it
so I'm going to say add actor you can
add an actor by drawing that actor
doing a character builder by the way
this guy's a character builder some cool
things you can do with character
builders like change their horns and
things like that we'll get into that
another video
or the media library and this is kinda
the one that I consider the most
common where I just use something from
there are several images now the thing I want is a
cupcake and so it's looks like there's a
lot of good options inside of here I'm
gonna pick the cupcake because I
like cupcakes but you can pick
anything you like now when you bring in
a sprite its image might be big or small
in the case of a cupcake it came in
quite big so I can just grab the handle
and just size it to whatever I want it
to be and then you can place it into
your scene into the spot that makes
sense so it's still about the same size
as the monster you must be a hungry
monster but the other cupcake was just a
little too big all right so let's go
ahead and look at the code for the
cupcake so you've noticed I've
accidentally clicked the stage here you can
switch through from different actors and
the stage and you can see what code
they've got so right now the cupcakes
got nothing so let's go ahead and make
some code for the cupcake and so the
first thing that I'm going to add for
the cupcake is the on start command this
is similar to scratch's when green flag
clicked so it's the same concept but
it's the most common way just to
actually add code that happens right at
the start and what we want to do is we
want to do something forever very common
to tell your your actors in your code to
do something forever be very mean to do
to a real person but in code just do
this forever and what he's gonna do is
he's gonna check to see if the monster
is touching him forever so if the
monster is touching him he wants to hide
and change a variable so we still got to
get into variables but that's his
whole mission in life so let's go ahead
and check if I'm touching the monster so
a check is an if statement and so it
says if some condition then run this
code now the some condition that I want
to put in here is am i touching the
monster so that's in sensing so you'll
get better with these different kinds of
different code blocks but what we want to do
is we want to know if we're touching the
monster or not now the command that I am
drawing in here is the top one if I'm
touching the mouse pointer that's
because mouse pointer you can change to
be something different and I want to
check if I'm touching the monster so
if touching monster then hide so hide
is at the very bottom od looks or near
the bottom so I'm going to take hide
here and put it right in there I can
test my code like as I build things so
the monster doesn't touch the
cupcake yet so it's not a very good test
just yet but if I were to put the
cupcake down in this path and hit run
you can see that it would in fact hide
the cupcake which is good now I do
have another problem my cupcake got
hidden but it never got shown again so
I'm gonna have to fix that so I'm gonna
take a show and put it right up here at
the top now one trick you can do to show
it is you can just hit play and then
stop right away and then your cupcake
will kind of be back I'm sure there's
some other good way I guess you could
probably just have like brought it
over and just like double clicked on
show or something like that to show but
I kind of just like play and pause
just to burn it back so I don't really
want my cupcake to be up here on the
table but my monster right now doesn't
go up and down right he just goes back
and forth so let's fix our monster a
little bit so our monster right now he
just always goes back and forth well I
want him to move still but I want him to
point at the mouse cursor as he does
things so that's going to be in motion
so inside motion you can see there's
this go-to mouse pointer that is not the
one we want if you put that in your code
what happens is he just stays with your
mouse pointer all the time right so it's
like instantaneous so that's not the one
we want so I'm gonna get that out of
there that would be bad and instead I
want point towards ah here it is very bottom point
towards mouse pointer and you can see
that the two are different so go-to is
bad point towards is what we want and so
now
he just kind of goes towards our mouse
pointer as I move it around and if I hit
the cupcake you can see that I
successfully got it and if I hit start
stop then I can bring my cupcake
back pretty easily cool so it's going
pretty good
so monster is moving around if he
gets to the mouse he kind of freaks out
a little bit that does make sense
because he moves past it so he turns
around then he comes back and then he
goes past it and he turns around he comes
back and he does this ping pong thing
back and forth
I consider that a feature I don't have a
need to fix it but since we're teaching
you stuff let's show you how to fix it
just so that you know if you wanted to
right and so the idea is this code right
now always points towards a mouse
pointer and always moves 30 pixels but I
want to not move 30 pixels if I'm
touching the mouse pointer so you heard
the word if in my explanation for what I
want to do so I'm gonna start with an if
statement so it's in control and what I
want to do is I only want to move in
certain situations right oh by the way
this if on edge bounce we don't need
this anymore right this is trash
code that was useful when we
weren't dieting but now we are dieting
and we don't need that trash that all
right so now it says if some condition
then move 30 pixels so I'm going to put
this back in my code right now so if some
condition which I haven't filled in yet
then move 30 pixels and this condition
is if I'm not touching the mouse pointer
so if I'm not touching the mouse pointer
then go so first I need a not nots
are in operators you have to scroll down
in operators until you find a not
here's not and I want if I'm not
touching the mouse pointer so if I'm not
touching the mouse pointer there I
didn't have to change the argument all
right so let's try that let's see if it
does it so if I'm not touching the mouse
pointer it moves like always but then if
I am touching the mouse pointer he stops
now he's also doing his little
animate thing even when he's touching the
mouse pointer and I don't like that so
I'm gonna take animate out and put it
inside here so now he will stop
animating when he hits the mouse pointer
now you notice there's a little bug here
too he kind of keeps walking until he
finishes that animation cycle maybe
I should make this stage a little bigger and so
when he hits the mouse he finishes his
animation cycle then he stops just let
things like that go you really should
but if you want to know how to fix this
one it's because there's animate which
is one way to change costumes and then
there's also switch costume now this is
interesting but walk is actually like a
list of costumes and if I exchange
animate walk to switch to costume
walk
it'll stop instantaneously right you'll
notice that as soon as he gets there he
stops so little details like that I
recommend that when
you're coding and you're learning you
don't worry about the details in the
family video that I did I didn't even go
through all that but for you guys for
the the kind of like short video I'm
showing you the little details right
cool so we've got a monster and he's
walking around and he could pick up
cupcakes but we've got a couple problems
one is we only have one cupcake but
before i duplicate my cupcakes i want to
change his code some and so what I really
want to do if you remember that
solution is he has a counter appear that
showed how much food was left so I need
to do two things I need to make a
variable and I need to add what's called
a watcher so I can see it so variables
are kind of one of the the points of
today so let's go ahead and make a
variable so variables are one of the
categories that's over here on the left
and you can create a variable now I'm
going to name my variable food and food
is going to be either global like for
all actors or local to just this
actor now I want food to be modified by
the cupcakes so I'm gonna say for all
actors that way it's globally available
that is gonna present a bug later but
we'll fix it so when I call it food
admittedly in a real app I might name it
like num food remaining or something
like that but but food is better because
it's short it's gonna show up in our
watcher just fine so now I've got this
variable food in general I like to go
ahead and set variables at the start of
my code so I'm gonna set food to be five
five right off the go and so now if I
run it my code it really is five it's
just you can't see it right so it's
under the hood it's hidden somewhere in
my computer right but I want to see it
just because we're learning about
variables now normally when you code you
have variables that aren't visible all
the time but since we're learning let's
definitely watch this variable the way
you do that is you click on the variable
itself and then you say add watcher and
what it does is it made this little box
in the middle of my screen which I'm
going to move up here
This surprised me but there's a
little bug inside the watcher code I
know it's hard to see in your screen
right now maybe I'll move this out of
the way a little there is a slider that you
can move across the bottom you can also
just grab it and move it here but it says
property food of monster for global
variables it's really supposed to say
property food of any I don't know why it
auto-generated the wrong code for you I
consider that a bug in Tynker but if
you want it work right you're gonna have
to go into the food watcher so it
created an actor for you and modify that
code so that it says any instead of
monster and you know it's working
because it will say food five at the top
here if it says food : with like nothing
there then it means that you have not
yet properly fixed that bug right ah
cool and it really shouldn't work with
monster I'm gonna try one more time but
yeah you can see see there whatever the
default code it shows up blank isn't that crazy
fix that tynker watch this video and
fix it
and it's only a bug for global variables
so what I want to do is when I break
collect this cupcake I want food to go
down now if you wanted you
could obviously start at zero and you
can make food go up but I'm gonna have a
countdown is kind of my goal so I'm
going to go into the code for my cupcake
and I'm going to modify my variable in
there now I don't want to set the
variable like I don't want to set it
to four I want to change it by one so I
want to change food by one and so I'm
going to say negative one because I want it
to go down alright cool so I'll go ahead
and so I'll pop up the stage just so we
can see that the counter is there
when I hit food it went to four which is
cool alright let's
mass produce cupcakes so I happen to
know that there's one more change that
I'm going to make to it later but I'm
gonna go ahead and mass-produce it now
so you can see the downside of early
mass production right so duplicate
and so there I now have five cupcakes
I'm gonna choose to set them on my scene
in different spots maybe I'll put a
couple on the floor or a couple of here
I do recommend that you don't put them
too close to your monster because if he
grabs them off the go it's gonna be hard
to figure out what's going on being
OCD I'm going to name my cupcakes you can
see it kind of tried to go in unique
names but it didn't like name them as
logically as I would have so I'm going
to rename them one two three four five
and so you just single click into that
area and rename them one two three four
five cool and so now if I run it as I
collect these things oops lets make it
bigger it says three two one and then
here it says zero now whenever I get to
zero nothing really happens right so
we're doing good but we want something
to happen we want the Monster to say you
win and the game to stop when we get to zero
so let's go and add that code so for the
monster
I want to always check if that variable
is zero so I need to add an if statement
you can put it anywhere inside the
monsters loop I'm gonna put it right at
the bottom and I want to check if that
variable is zero well all my cupcakes
are gone i want them back so I hit play stop
alright now they're back so if that variable is
zero then do stuff equals is an operator
so we've got to go into the operators
area and here's equals and we'll just
drop it in here and we want to say if
food is equal to zero then we want to do
stuff now if you wanted to you could
have made food start at zero and you
could make each of these count up and
then this would be like it food equals
five but mine's a countdown
so I want food equals zero now if that
happens I want to say you win so I'm
gonna go to looks and I'm gonna find
a say block so there's really complex
scary ones up here and then there's
really simple ones down here I actually
want one of the complex scary ones and
I'm going to drop it in here and the
reason I want a complex scary one is
because it's got all the options that I
can set so I can set the text obviously
I'm gonna make it say you win I can set
what type of text box it is I'm gonna go
with a rectangular like speech bubble
the default one by the way just puts a
message at the bottom of the screen
which is cool but not what we want
here and then for speech bubbles I
happened to know that 18 is a really small
font I so I'm gonna bump it up to
48 so I set the text set the style to
rectangular and then I set this to 48
and then the last thing I want to do is
I want to put a stop all immediately
after that text message so I'm going
to put it immediately after that text
message I'm gonna go and run it just
to see if it works so I grab a donut or
a cupcake cupcake two left and 0 so now
it says you win and the game comes to a
stop which is cool great so almost done
probably worth saving so I'm gonna click on the Save
button for now so I'm just gonna save
I'll tell what I'll do an and publish
later right now I'm still working on
it so I'm just gonna click Save
I want to fix some other little things
but I first want to show you another bug
so it happens all the time where people
accidentally instead of putting this
right below the statement there they put
it right here
now that's of course terrible because
the if statement only consists of these
things and the stop statement is
actually just right inside the forever
we break so the forever loop has the
stop statement inside of it and so when
I run my code it's just gonna
immediately stop and that's because the
first time through this loop it doesn't
point towards it does this if check it
waits does this if check and then stops
right now things like that really get
people because you're like oh my monster
stopped moving and go panic one thing you
can do is you can try to look at your
code but also this debug button can be
handy as well so if I click on this
debug button and I hit play what it'll
do is it will let me do that a little
slower so if I hit play you can see it
goes through and shows you each line of
code like as it's running and telling
you what's happening and then
when it gets to the bottom you can see
that it's hitting the stop all maybe
that's useful to you another thing you
can do is I believe you can step through
it slower
I'm not a master of the debugger you
know you can set breakpoints that's what
you can do in the bottom of control you
can put a breakpoint in and so you
know you put a breakpoint in and you can
see what happens like when it when it
hits your breakpoint right now of course
if you put a breakpoint there you've
obviously figured out what the problem
is but I just wanted to point out the
debugger because it can be useful when
you're trying to figure out these
stumpers and of course the problem is
that was just in the wrong spot
ah cool so game almost complete I'm
going to add one more feature i want the
monster to start slow and then get
faster I'm going to need another
variable so in variables I'm going to
say create variable and I'm going to
create a variable called speed and then
speed I'm going to let the cupcakes
change it so I'm gonna say it's for all
actors but really just the
monster uses it by the way you can set a
reset value if you wanted so let's say
we wanted him to reset to ten and that
will make sure that the variable
automatically gets reset for you now
I rarely do that trick the reset variable
I was just showing you that it's
possible and that's because I like for
it to actually be in my code so I can
see it right so I like to say in my code
set speed so I'm on the monster's code
now set speed to be ten and then I can
see it in my code as opposed to you know
they're reset on stop trick
reset on stop is useful but I prefer to
just put it in here now I want to use
speed so I want speed to be right
here so right now all I've done is I've
just made the game slower right because
I went from 30 to ten what I want the
cupcakes to do is I want cupcakes to
increase speed so cupcakes now have two
functions they make food go down and
they make speed go up right now I've
only modified cupcake one so whenever I
get like cupcake two you know
nothing really happens or this cupcake
nothing really happens now whenever I hit
the one that is cupcake one which
was that one it did speed up but
obviously I want this this piece of code
on all my cupcakes what I'm going to do
is I'm going to drag and drop it on the
dot cupcake and that one and that one
and that one so what that did is that
actually put it somewhere in their block
of code but it didn't actually put it in
the right place so that way I just need
to go through each one and drop it into
the right place now whenever you have
multiple duplicates there are more
elegant ways to do it with clones but I
thought I'd just kind of show you a
simple
way to kind of do things great so I
think we've got a finished game so if I
run it I can see there's chasing the
mouse pointer it's going nice and slow
and then as he hits cupcakes
he hit begins to speed up cool so you win
all right so I'm ready to be done with
this thing I'm going to go ahead and
click on publish to community I just so
other people can see this and so this
is my connecting with code week one day
one exercise so I'll hit save and
publish hey since this is kind of
the advanced video maybe we'll do one
more thing together as well and the
thing that I wouldn't mind doing
together is making another example just
because it can be nice to make multiple
examples let's go ahead and see if we
can make one more actually maybe I
should make that a different video so
I'll cut this video off here and then
we'll do the other example in a separate
video
alright see you next time thanks for
joining us for connecting with code keep
doing this stuff also make sure you're
doing some of the like puzzle levels on
your own
it's like dragon spells or Barbie
space-cadet those can be fun things to
work and they'll get you thinking about
code a lot better alright see you later
bye
[Music]